Leah: Therapy can often vary in scope,
they may be provided one-to-one, in
a group, online, over the phone, or
with family in a health care centre
setting, but what therapies all
have in common is that they take
place with a trained therapist.
Rhiannon: If the waiting lists for
‘Talking therapies’ available on the NHS
are too long in an area, there are also
private agencies or independent services.
These have to be paid for and
this type of service is run like
a business, but can be much more
accessible and much more immediate.
Leah: Some parents of children
and young people, may wish to seek
independent care because they feel a
more specialist targeted treatment is
needed, over a longer period of time.
Sometimes they may feel treatment
in a private clinic or hospital
is more appropriate for them.
Rhiannon: All health professionals are
available privately as well as through
NHS channels, including GPs, Therapists
and Counsellors, and Psychiatrists.
The costs of treatment and support
can vary depending upon the type and
duration of the treatment, but private
treatment can work very favourably
for those who want help immediately
and have the ability to pay for it.
Leah: GPs should be able to
signpost an individual to specific
professionals, whether this is
through the NHS or privately.
Therapists and counsellors can be
approached directly or by referral and
there are many organisations online that
can recommend or showcase these services.
Rhiannon: Therapy is a good alternative
or complementary approach to mental health
care and if the individual is willing to
do the work, therapy can be rewarding.
Therapies like CBT also include
Self-help books and computer courses
and guided self-help is recommended
as a treatment for depression,
anxiety and panic disorder.
Guided self-help aims to give helpful
tools and techniques that can carry on
being used after the course has finished.
Leah: Therapy is a safe, judgment-free
space, where an individual can share
anything with a trained professional,
who is there to improve mental health
and increase mind and body wellness,
without relying on medication.